<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: convolution-deconvolution.xml 22529 2019-09-29 09:37:42Z dn2010 $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='convolution-deconvolution'>
  <title>Convolution and deconvolution</title>
  <para>
    Several Gwyddion functions do convolutions and deconvolutions of some sort.
    A subtle point which is occasionaly a source of confusion is the difference
    between continuous and discrete operations.  When images
    <xi:include href='eqi-f.xml'/> and <xi:include href='eqi-g.xml'/> are
    physical quantities, i.e. fields sampled in space, their convolution
    <xi:include href='eqi-h.xml'/>
    <xi:include href="eq-convolution-continuous.xml"/>
    is again a physical field.  Its physical dimension (units) is
    <xi:include href="eq-convolution-units.xml"/>
    For images <xi:include href="eqi-dim-A.xml"/> has the dimension of image
    area, i.e. usually square metres.
  </para>
  <para>
    When the integral is realized using a discrete Riemann sum
    <xi:include href="eq-convolution-Riemann-sum.xml"/>
    the area appears as the area of one pixel
    <xi:include href="eqi-Delta-A.xml"/>.  This is how all Gwyddion
    convolution, deconvolution and transfer function operations work by
    default, i.e.  with the <guilabel>Normalize as integral</guilabel> option
    enabled.
  </para>
  <para>
    In digital image processing physical units are sometimes ignored and
    convolution understood as simple discrete convolution of images
    <xi:include href="eq-convolution-discrete.xml"/>
    It is possible to obtain this behaviour by disabling the option
    <guilabel>Normalize as integral</guilabel> in a particular function.  You
    should be aware the result of the operation is then no longer a physical
    quantity sampled in space (it depends on pixel size) and the units are
    different.  The only function which works this way by default is
    <link linkend='convolution-filter'>Convolution Filter</link>, where one
    of the operands is given as a small matrix of unitless numbers.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='convolve'>
    <title>
      Image convolution <gwy:icon name='convolve'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>convolution</primary>
      <secondary>of two images</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>transfer function</primary>
      <secondary>convolution</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Multidata</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Convolve</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Convolution of two images can be performed using Convolve
      (see <link linkend='convolution-filter'>Convolution Filter</link> for
      convolution with a small kernel, entered numerically).  The module has
      only a few options:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Convolution kernel</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          The smaller image to convolve the larger image with, for instance
          a tip transfer function image. The dimensions of one pixel in both
          images must correspond.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Exterior type</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          What values should be assumed for pixels outside the image
          (as in <link linkend='extend'>Extend</link>).
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Output size</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          The size of the resulting image with respect to which pixels entered
          the calculation.  <guilabel>Crop to interior</guilabel> cuts the
          image to consists only of pixels that are sufficiently far from the
          boundary that the exterior does not matter.  <guilabel>Keep
          size</guilabel> creates an image with the same as the input image.
          Finally, <guilabel>Extend to convolved</guilabel> means the resulting
          image will be extended on each side by half the kernel size.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='deconvolve'>
    <title>
      Image deconvolution <gwy:icon name='deconvolve'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>deconvolution</primary>
      <secondary>of two images</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Multidata</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Deconvolve</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      A simple regularized deconvolution of two images can be performed using
      Deconvolve.  L-curve method can be used to search for the optimum
      regularization parameter, however its applicability highly depends on
      the data. The module has the following options:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Convolution kernel</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          The kernel to be deconvolved from the current image.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Sigma</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          Regularization parameter.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>L-curve display</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          The data to be shown in the optional L-curve plot, when this is
          computed. The L-curve consist of two data sources: difference between
          the result convolved with the kernel and the original data and norm
          of the result. These two are plotted in a log-log graph providing
          a L-curve, but their dependences on the regularization parameters can
          be plotted also individually. The curvature of the resulting curve
          vs. regularization parameter gives the usual criterion for the best
          regularization parameters, seeking for the curve maximum.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>L-curve sigma range</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          Range of the regularization parameter to be used in the L-curve
          calculation. This is, similarly to the regularization parameter,
          logarithmic, so it can span very large range, not necessarily
          suitable for the particular data set.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Output type <guilabel>Deconvolved</guilabel> produces the deconvolved
      image; <guilabel>Difference</guilabel> calculates the difference between
      reconvolved image and the input.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='deconvolve-dialogue'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='deconvolve-dialogue.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Screenshot of the deconvolve dialogue after L-curve data were computed.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </sect2>
  <sect2 id='transfer-function'>
    <title>
      Transfer function estimation
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>transfer function</primary>
      <secondary>estimation</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>point spread function</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      The <emphasis>probe transfer function</emphasis> (or point spread
      function) can be estimated from measured data, even noisy, when the
      corresponding ideally sharp signal is available.  Gwyddion currently
      implements a few relatively simple methods.
    </para>
    <para id='transfer-function-guess'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Processing</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Statistics</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Transfer Function Guess</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      The user interface of the module is and a typical performance
      on simulated noisy data is shown in the following figures.
    </para>
    <para>
      The sharp signal is selected as <guilabel>Ideal response</guilabel>.  It
      must have the same dimensions as the image.  In contrast to the general Deconvolve module
      this module is optimized for the statistical properties of the transfer functions.
      There are currently three available deconvolution methods:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Regularised filter</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Simple frequency-space filter with constant regularisation term.
            It produces transfer function image of the same size as the input
            images.  Option <guilabel>TF zoom</guilabel> can be used to display
            zoomed central part of the image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Least squares</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The transfer function is found by solving the least squares problem
            corresponding to the deconvolution.  The size of transfer function
            can be chosen arbitrarily.  Usually it is much smaller than the
            input images.
          </para>
          <para>
            Parameter <guilabel>Size</guilabel> controls the transfer function
            image size.  If <guilabel>Border</guilabel> is nonzero, the
            transfer function image is enlarged by this value before solving
            the least squares problem and then the border is cut.  A small
            border of 2 or 3 often improves the result because errors tend to
            accumulate in the edge pixels.  Both sizes can be estimated
            automatically using <guibutton>Estimate Size</guibutton>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Wiener filter</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Pseudo-Wiener filter assuming the spectral density of the output
            can be estimated by the spectral density of the input image.
            It is again a frequency-domain filter, producing transfer function
            image of the same size as the input images.  Option <guilabel>TF
            zoom</guilabel> can be used to display zoomed central part of the
            image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Two important parameters influence the result.  The dimensionless
      regularisation parameter <xi:include href='eqi-sigma.xml'/>, which
      is used in all the methods, but is not directly comparable between them.
      It can be chosen manually.  Since suitable values can differ by several
      orders of magnitude, it is presented as base-10 logarithm.  However, the
      module can find a suitable value also automatically when <guibutton>Fit
      Sigma</guibutton> is pressed.
    </para>
    <para>
      <guibutton>Windowing type</guibutton> determines the
      <link linkend='windowing'>windowing function</link> applied to both
      input images before deconvolution.  Unless the input data are periodic,
      windowing is a necessity to avoid cross-like artefacts in the transfer
      function.  The default Welch window is usually a good choice.
    </para>
    <para>
      A few characteristics of the transfer function are immediately displayed
      in the bottom part of the dialogue as <guilabel>Result</guilabel>:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>TF width</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          Width, calculated as square root of dispersion when the transfer
          function is taken as a distribution.  Only the central peak is
          included in the calculation (which is important namely for
          regularised and Wiener filters).  Usually, the optimal reconstruction
          has also small width.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>TF height</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          Maximum value of the transfer function.  When it starts to decrease
          noticeably, the regularisation parameter is probably too high.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>TF norm</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          Mean square value of the transfer function.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Difference norm</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          Mean square value of the difference between the input image and
          ideal sharp image convolved with the reconstructed transfer function.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The tab <guilabel>Output Options</guilabel> allows choosing the images
      the function will produce: the transfer function (<guilabel>Transfer
      function</guilabel>), its convolution with the ideal sharp image
      (<guilabel>Convolved</guilabel>) and/or the difference between the
      input and the convolved image (<guilabel>Difference</guilabel>).
      For methods which produce full-size transfer function images,
      <guilabel>Only zoomed part</guilabel> limits the output image size to
      the zoomed part displayed in the dialogue.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-psf-guess-dialogue'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='psf-guess-dialogue.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Screenshot of the transfer function estimation module.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <informalfigure id='fig-psf-guess-apps'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='psf-guess-apps.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Sample results of the transfer function estimation module.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para id='transfer-function-fit'>
      An alternative method of TF estimation is the fitting of an explicit
      function form, for instance Gaussian.  The free parameters of the
      function are sought to minimise the sum of squared differences between
      measured data and ideal response convolved with the TF.  Since the
      minimisation can be performed entirely in the frequency domain and does
      not require repeated convolution, this method is simple and fast, albeit
      somewhat crude.  It is available as
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Processing</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Statistics</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Transfer Function Fit</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      with three model functions currently implemented: fully symmetrical
      Gaussian, anisotropic Gaussian which can have different widths
      in the horizontal and vertical directions, and TF which is exponential
      in the frequency space.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
