<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: edit-extended.xml 26077 2024-01-02 13:46:31Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='edit-extended' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
  <title>Global Distortions</title>
  <para>
     This section presents extended functions for correction (or creation)
     of global errors, such as low frequencies modulated on the data or drift
     in the slow scanning axis.  Most of the functions described below
     deal with distortion purely in the
     <xi:include href="eqi-xy.xml"/> plane – for instance
     <link linkend='drift-compensation'>Drift Compensation</link>
     or <link linkend='straighten-path'>Straighten Path</link>.
     Some modify the value distribution (<link linkend='coerce'>Coerce</link>)
     or perform complex operations involving both coordinates and values.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='drift-compensation'>
    <title>
      Drift Compensation <gwy:icon name='drift'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>drift compensation</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distortion</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Compensate Drift</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Compensate Drift calculates and/or corrects drift in the fast scanning
      axis (horizontal).  This adverse effect can be caused by thermal
      effects or insufficient mechanical rigidity of the measuring device.
    </para>
    <para>
      The drift graph, which is one of possible outputs,
      represents the horizontal shift of individual rows compared to
      a reference row (which could be in principle chosen arbitrarily, in
      practice the zero shift is chosen to minimize the amount of data
      sticking out of the image after compensation), with the row
      <xi:include href="eqi-y.xml"/>-coordinate on the abscissa.
    </para>
    <para>
      The drift is determined in two steps:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          A mutual horizontal offset is estimated for each couple of rows not
          more distant than <guilabel>Search range</guilabel>.  It is
          estimated as the offset value giving the maximum mutual correlation
          of the two rows.  Thus a set of local row drift estimations is
          obtained (together with the maximum correlation scores providing
          an estimate of their actual similarity).
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Global offsets are calculated from the local ones.  At present the
          method is very simple as it seems sufficient in most cases: local
          drift derivatives are fitted for each row onto the local drift
          estimations and the global drift is then obtained by integration
          (i.e. summing the local drifts).
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Option <guilabel>Exclude linear skew</guilabel> subtracts the linear
      term from the calculated drift, it can be useful when the image is
      anisotropic and its features are supposed to be oriented in a direction
      not paralled to the image sides.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-drift-correction'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='drift-corrected-graph.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Drift correction example:
          (a) original data exhibiting strong drift in the fast scan axis,
          (b) corrected data,
          (c) calculated drift graph.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='correct-affine'>
    <title>
      Affine Distortion <gwy:icon name='correct_affine'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
       <primary>distortion in xy plane</primary>
       <secondary>affine</secondary>
     </indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distortion</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Affine</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Affine distortion in the horizontal plane caused by thermal drift is
      common for instance in STM.  If the image contains a regular structure,
      for instance an atomic lattice of known parameters, the distortion can
      be easily corrected using this function.
    </para>
    <para>
      The affine distortion correction requires to first select the distorted
      lattice in the image.  This is done by moving the lattice selection on
      the preview with mouse until it matches the regular features present in
      the image.  For images of periodic lattices, it is usually easier to
      select the lattice in the autocorrelation function image
      (<guilabel>2D ACF</guilabel>).
      Also, only a rough match needs to be found manually in this case.  Button
      <guibutton>Refine</guibutton> refines the selected lattice vectors to the
      nearest maxima in autocorrelation function with subpixel precision.
    </para>
    <para>
      If scan lines contain lots of high-frequency noise the horizontal ACF
      (middle row in the ACF image) can be also quite noisy.  In such case
      it is better to interpolate it from the surrounding rows by enabling
      the option <guilabel>Interpolate horizontal ACF</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The correct lengths of the lattice vectors
      <xi:include href="eqi-a_1.xml"/> and <xi:include href="eqi-a_2.xml"/>
      and the angle <xi:include href="eqi-phi.xml"/> between them, entered to
      the dialogue, determine the affine transformation to perform.  A few common
      lattice types (such as HOPG surface) are offered predefined, but it is
      possible to enter arbitrary lengths and angle.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-affine-correction'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='correct-affine.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='correct-affine.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Affine correction example:
          (a) original image exhibiting an affine distortion,
          (b) correction dialogue with the lattice selected on the
              two-dimensional autocorrelation,
          (c) corrected image.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      It should be noted that the correction method described above causes all
      lateral scale information in the image to be lost because the new lateral
      scale is fully determined by the correct lattice vectors.  This is
      usually the best option for STM images of known atomic lattices, however,
      for a general skew or affine correction it can be impractical.
      Therefore, the dialogue offers three different scaling choices:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Exactly as specified</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Lattice vectors in the corrected image will have the specified
            lengths and angle between them.  Scale information of the original
            image is discarded completely.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Preserve area</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Lattice vectors in the corrected image will have the specified
            ratio of lengths and angle between them.  However, the overall
            scale is calculated as to make the affine transformation
            area-preserving.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Preserve X scale</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Lattice vectors in the corrected image will have the specified
            ratio of lengths and angle between them.  However, the overall
            scale is calculated as to make the affine transformation
            preserve the original <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/>-axis scale.
            This is somewhat analogous to the scale treatment in
            <link linkend='drift-compensation'>Drift compensation</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The function can also correct one image using the ACF calculated from
      another image (presumably a different channel in the same measurement) or
      apply the correction to all images in the file.  The former is
      accomplished by selecting a different image as <guilabel>Image for
      ACF</guilabel> in the options.  Affine transformation of all images in
      the file is enabled by <guilabel>Apply to all compatible
      images</guilabel>.  Both options requite the other images to be
      compatible with the current one, i.e. having the same pixel and real
      dimensions.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='correct-perspective'>
    <title>
      Perspective Distortion
    </title>
    <indexterm>
       <primary>distortion in xy plane</primary>
       <secondary>perspective</secondary>
     </indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distortion</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Perspective</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Perspective distortion is unusual in scanning probe microscopy, but
      relatively common in other types of image data.  The perspective
      distortion module can correct such distortion if the image contains
      features which are known to be in fact rectangular.
    </para>
    <para>
      To apply the correction, a perspective rectangle is selected on the image
      by moving its four corners.  The selected region is then transformed and
      extracted to the result.  The preview can be switched between original
      and corrected data.
    </para>
    <para>
      The module sets the pixel and physical dimensions of the result to
      estimated reasonable values, based on the assumption the distortion is
      not large.  The dimensions then more or less correspond to the dimensions
      of the selected distorted rectangle in the original image.  However,
      it is just an estimate.  If the dimensions of the extracted rectangle can
      be determined more precisely, for instance using markings in the image,
      they should be set using
      <link linkend='dimensions-and-units'>Dimensions and Units</link>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-perspective-correction'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='correct-perspective.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='correct-perspective.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Perspective correction example.
          Left: original image exhibiting an perspective distortion.
          Centre: correction dialogue with the rectangle selected in the
              image.
          Right: corrected image.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      Option <guilabel>Create new image</guilabel> controls whether the image
      is replaced with corrected or a new image created. The function can also
      apply the correction to all compatible images in the file.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='polynomial-distort'>
    <title>
      Polynomial Distortion <gwy:icon name='poly_distort'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
       <primary>distortion in xy plane</primary>
       <secondary>polynomial</secondary>
     </indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distortion</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Polynomial</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      General distortion in the horizontal plane can be compensated, or
      created, with Polynomial distortion.  It performs transforms that
      can be expressed as
    </para>
    <xi:include href="eq-polynomial-distortion.xml"/>
    <para>
      where <xi:include href="eqi-P_x.xml"/> and
      <xi:include href="eqi-P_y.xml"/> are polynomials up to the third total
      degree with user-defined coefficients.  Note the direction of the
      coordinate transform – the reverse direction would not guarantee an
      unambiguous mapping.
    </para>
    <para>
      The polynomial coefficients are entered as scale-free, i.e.
      as if the coordinate ranges were always [0, 1].  If
      <guilabel>Instant updates</guilabel> are enabled, pressing
      <keycap>Enter</keycap> in a coefficient entry (or just leaving moving
      keyboard focus elsewhere) updates the preview.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='straighten-path'>
    <title>
      Straighten Path <gwy:icon name='straighten_path'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
       <primary>distortion in xy plane</primary>
       <secondary>along path</secondary>
     </indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distortion</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Straighten Path</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Extraction of data along circular features, curved step edges and other
      arbitrarily shaped smooth paths can be a useful preprocessing step for
      further analysis.  Function <guimenuitem>Straighten Path</guimenuitem>
      creates a new image by <quote>straightening</quote> the input image
      along a spline path specified using a set of points on the image.
    </para>
    <para>
      The points defining the path can be defined on the preview image.
      Each control point can be moved with mouse.  Clicking into the empty
      space adds a new point, connected to the closer end of the path.
      Individual points can be deleted by selecting them in the point list in
      the left part of the dialogue and pressing <keycap>Delete</keycap>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The shape of the extracted area is controlled by the following
      parameters:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Thickness</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The width of the extracted image, denoted by the perpendicular
            marks on the path.  This is the full width, i.e. the distance to
            each side of the path is half of the thickness.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Slackness</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Parameter influencing the shape of the path between the control
            points.  It can be visualised as the slackness of a string
            connecting the control points.  For zero slackness the string is
            taut and the path is formed by straight segments.  Increasing
            slackness means decreasing tensile stress in the string, up to
            slackness of unity for which the string is stress-free.  Values
            larger than unity mean there is an excess string length, leading to
            compressive stress.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Closed curve</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If this option is enabled the path is closed, allowing the
            extraction of ring-shaped areas (for instance).  Otherwise the
            path has two free ends.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Pressing <guibutton>Update</guibutton> computes a preview of the extracted image
      and shows it to the right of the input image.  The preview is displayed vertically,
      with top edge corresponding to the path beginning and bottom edge to its end.
      The extracted image can be either oriented the same way or horizontally (from left
      to right), depending on <guilabel>Output orientation</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para>
      For certain combinations of path shape and thickness the resulting image
      can contain regions that lie outside the original image.  Such regions
      are masked in the output and filled with a neutral value.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-straighten-path'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='straighten-path.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Straighten Path example, showing extraction of data along a closed
          circular path.  The left part of the dialogue contains coordinates of
          the path-defining points and function options, the middle part shows
          the selected circular path (with perpendicular markers denoting the
          thickness), and the right part is a preview of the extracted
          straightened data.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='extract-path-selection'>
    <title>
      Extract Path Selection <gwy:icon name='extract_path'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distortion</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Extract Path Selection</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Function <link linkend='straighten-path'>Straighten Path</link> stores
      the selected path with the data so that it can be recalled later.  If you
      need the coordinates and/or directions corresponding to the straightened
      image for further processing you can use
      <guimenuitem>Extract Path Selection</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The function plots the real coordinates or tangents to the path,
      i.e. the direction cosines and sines, as graphs.  Coordinates are
      selected as <guilabel>X position</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>Y position</guilabel>; directions are selected as
      <guilabel>X tangent</guilabel> and <guilabel>Y tangent</guilabel>.
      The number of points of each graph curve is the same as the number of
      rows of the straightened image created by
      <link linkend='straighten-path'>Straighten Path</link>
      and there is one-to-one correspondence between the rows and graph curve
      points.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <!-- FIXME: This one now does not really belong here, but it does not really
       belong anywhere and this is the closest... -->
  <sect2 id='unrotate'>
    <title>
      Unrotate <gwy:icon name='unrotate'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>rotation correction</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>unrotate</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Unrotate</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Unrotate can automatically make principal directions in an image
      parallel with horizontal and/or vertical image edges.  For that to work,
      the data need to have some principal directions, therefore it is most
      useful for scans of artificial and possibly crystalline structures.
    </para>
    <para>
      The rotation necessary to straighten the image – displayed
      as <guilabel>Correction</guilabel> – is calculated from peaks
      in angular <link linkend='slope-distribution'>slope distribution</link>
      assuming a prevalent type of structure, or symmetry.
      The symmetry can be estimated automatically too, but it is possible to
      select a particular symmetry type manually and let the module calculate
      only corresponding rotation correction.  Note if you assume a
      structure type that does not match the actual structure, the calculated
      rotation is rarely meaningful.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is recommended to level (or
      <link linkend='facet-level'>facet-level</link>) the data
      first as overall slope can skew the calculated rotations.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-unrotate-directions'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='unrotate-symmetries.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='unrotate-symmetries.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Unrotate symmetries scheme</phrase>
        </textobject>
        <caption>
          Orientations of prevalent directions corresponding to Unrotate
          symmetry types.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      The assumed structure type can be set with <guilabel>Assume</guilabel>
      selector.  Following choices are possible:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            Detected
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Automatically detected symmetry type, displayed above as
              <guilabel>Detected</guilabel>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            Parallel
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Parallel lines, one prevalent direction.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            Triangular
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Triangular symmetry, three prevalent directions (unilateral) by
              120 degrees.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            Square
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Square symmetry, two prevalent directions oriented
              approximately along image sides.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            Rhombic
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Rhombic symmetry, two prevalent directions oriented approximately
              along diagonals.  The only difference from Square is the
              preferred diagonal orientation (as opposed to parallel with
              sides).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            Hexagonal
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Hexagonal symmetry, three prevalent directions (bilateral) by 120
              degrees.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='displacement-field'>
    <title>
      Displacement Field
    </title>
    <para>
      Displacement field is a general method of image distortion in the
      <xi:include href="eqi-xy.xml"/> plane.  A vector is assigned to each
      point in the output image.  This vector determines how far and in which
      direction to move from this point.  The value found at the shifted
      position in the source image becomes the value of the pixel in the output
      image:
    </para>
    <xi:include href="eq-displacement-field-transform.xml"/>
    <para>
      where <xi:include href='eqi-vec-v.xml'/> is the displacement vector.
    </para>
    <para>
      The displacement field can be generated or obtained by several methods:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Gaussian (scan lines)</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The vectors have only the
            <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> component.
            The displacement is one-dimensional, along scan lines
            (image rows). It is a random Gaussian image, similar to Gaussian
            images generated by <link linkend='spectral-synthesis'>Spectral
            Synthesis</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Gaussian (two-dimensional)</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The vectors have both
            <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> and
            <xi:include href="eqi-y.xml"/> components, so the displacement
            is two-dimensional.
            It is again a random Gaussian image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Tear scan lines</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The vectors have only the
            <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> component.
            The displacement is one-dimensional, along scan lines
            (image rows). It is generated to tear segments of neighbour
            rows by shifting one to the left and another to the right.  In the
            rest of the image the displacement is smooth (and close to zero)
            so continuity is preserved outside the tear.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Image (scan lines)</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The vectors have only the
            <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> component.
            The displacement is one-dimensional, along scan lines
            (image rows), and given by another image (selected as
            <guilabel>X displacement</guilabel>).  The values of the image
            are directly used as the displacement vectors and must have the
            same units as lateral coordinates of the deformed image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Image (two-dimensional)</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The vectors have both
            <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/> and
            <xi:include href="eqi-y.xml"/> components, so the displacement
            is two-dimensional.
            They are given by another images (selected as <guilabel>X
            displacement</guilabel> and <guilabel>Y displacement</guilabel>).
            The values of the images are directly used as the displacement
            vectors and must have the same units as lateral coordinates of the
            deformed image.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='coerce'>
    <title>
      Coerce <gwy:icon name='enforce_distribution'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distortion</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Coerce</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      The module transforms the values in a height field to enforce certain
      prescribed statistical properties.  The distribution of values can be
      transformed to Gaussian, with mean value and rms roughness preserved,
      or uniform, with minimum and maximum value preserved.  It is also
      possible to enforce the same distribution as another height field
      selected as <guilabel>Template</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The transformation preserves the ordering of the values, i.e. if one
      point is higher than another before the transformation it will be also
      higher after the transformation.  Option <guilabel>Data
      processing</guilabel> controls whether the transformation is applied
      to the image as a whole (<guilabel>Entire image</guilabel>) or
      each row separately, with the same distribution
      (<guilabel>By row (identically)</guilabel>).  Note that in the latter
      case if a template is selected each row of the transformed image will
      have the same value distribution (approximately) as the template.
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition, a different kind of transformation can be performed,
      discretisation of the values into given number of levels.  This operation
      is selected with <guilabel>Discrete levels</guilabel>.  There are two
      different discretisations available, either the height levels are
      equidistant from minimum to maximum value (<guilabel>Uniform</guilabel>)
      or they are calculated so that after the transformation each level
      will consist of approximately the same number of pixels
      (<guilabel>Same area</guilabel>).
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='radial-smoothing'>
    <title>
      Radial Smoothing
    </title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Distortion</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Radial Smoothing</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      Radial smoothing processes the image with a Gaussian smoothing filter,
      but in polar coordinates.  This function is useful for images which
      should be relatively smooth and exhibit radial symmetry.
    </para>
    <para>
      The image can be smoothed either along radial profiles – with Gaussian
      filter width controlled by <guilabel>Radius</guilabel> – or angularly
      along arcs of constant radius from the centre – with width controlled
      by <guilabel>Angle</guilabel>. The transformation to polar coordinates
      and back does not preserve the image perfectly.  Subtle (and occasionally
      less subtle) artefacts can occur, in particular close to the centre,
      even with no actual smoothing.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
