<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: graph.xml 25722 2023-09-26 15:53:31Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='graph-processing'>
  <title>Graph Processing</title>
  <para>
    Many of the Gwyddion data processing modules produce graph as an output.
    Graphs can be exported into text files or further analysed within
    Gwyddion by several graph processing modules. These modules can be found
    in the Graph menu in the Gwyddion main window. Note that the number of
    graph modules is quite limited now and consists of basic modules for
    doing things that are very frequent within SPM data analysis. For more
    analytical tools you can use your favourite graph processing program.
  </para>
  <para>
    In this section the graph modules present in Gwyddion are briefly
    presented.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='basic-graph-operations'>
    <title>
      Basic Operations
      <gwy:icon name='graph_zoom_in'/>
      <gwy:icon name='logscale_horizontal'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      First of all zooming and data reading functions are available directly
      in the graph window:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        Logarithmic axes – horizontal and vertical axes can be switched
        between linear and logarithmic using the logscale buttons.  Switching
        to logarithmic scale is possible only for positive values (either on
        abscissa or ordinate).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Zoom in and zoom out – after selecting zoom in simply draw the area
        that should be zoomed by mouse. Zoom out restores the state where all
        data can be seen.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Measure distances – enables user to select several points within
        the graph and displays their distances and angles between them.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-flip'>
    <title>
      Graph Flip
    </title>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Graph Flip</guilabel> flips the graph vertically.  In other words
      the ordinate is inverted, whereas the abscissa is kept untouched.  The
      functions directly modifies the curve data; it does not just change the
      presentation.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-invert'>
    <title>
      Graph Invert
    </title>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Graph Invert</guilabel> flips the graph horizontally.  In other words
      the abscissa is inverted, whereas the ordinate is kept untouched.  The
      functions directly modifies the curve data; it does not just change the
      presentation.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-cut'>
    <title>
      Graph Cut <gwy:icon name='graph_cut'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Graph Cut</guilabel> is a very simple module that cuts graph
      curves to the selected range (either given numerically or on the graph
      with mouse) and creates a new graph.  If <guilabel>Cut all
      curves</guilabel> all curves are cut and put to the new graph; otherwise
      just the one chosen curve.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-level'>
    <title>
      Graph Level <gwy:icon name='graph_level'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      Graph level is also a simple module that currently performs linear fit of
      each graph curve and subtracts the fitted linear functions from them.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-align'>
    <title>
      Graph Align <gwy:icon name='graph_align'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      Graph align shifts the graphs curves horizontally to maximise their
      mutual correlations, i.e. match common features in the curves.  This is
      useful in particular for comparison of profiles taken in different
      locations.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-merge'>
    <title>
      Graph Merge and Average
    </title>
    <para>
      Two simple functions combine data of all curves to one, which is added to
      the plot. They differ slightly by data averaging approach.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guimenuitem>Merge Curves</guimenuitem>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          simply collects the data from all curves. It only merges two
          data points if the abscssae are the same, averaging the ordinates. The resulting
          curve thus usually oscillates between points belonging to the input curves if
          they are slightly vertically shifted.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guimenuitem>Average Curves</guimenuitem>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          attempts to combine close points, averaging both ordinates and abscissae. Usually
          the resulting curve has a similar (or somewhat larger) number of points to one
          input curve, not all of them together. It should be also much smoother than for the
          simple merge, although sometimes there can be still visible oscillations.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-logscale'>
    <title>Logscale Transform</title>
    <para>
      The graph window controls allow switching between linear and logarithmic
      axes.  However, for the fitting of power-law-like dependencies it is
      often useful to physically transform the data by taking logarithms of the
      values.  The logscale transform graph function performs such
      transformation.  You can choose which axis to transform
      (<xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/>, <xi:include href="eqi-y.xml"/> or both),
      what to do with non-positive values if they occur and the logarithm base.
      A new graph is then created, with all curves transformed as requested.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-export'>
    <title>
      Exporting Graph Curves
      <gwy:icon name='graph_export_ascii'/>
      <gwy:icon name='graph_export_png'/>
      <gwy:icon name='graph_export_vector'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>text export</primary>
      <secondary>graphs</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      Graph curve data can be exported to text files using
      <guimenuitem>Export Text</guimenuitem>.  The export dialogue allows
      choosing several style variations that particular other software may find
      easier to read.  Options
      <guilabel>Export labels</guilabel>,
      <guilabel>Export units</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>Export metadata</guilabel>
      allow adding informational lines before the actual data.  This can be
      very useful for reminding what the file contains, but may cause problems
      when the file is read in other software.
    </para>
    <para>
      Option <guilabel>POSIX number format</guilabel> enforces standard
      machine-readable scientific number format with decimal dot.  Otherwise
      the values are written according to locale settings (office-style
      software may like that; scientific software generally does not).
    </para>
    <para>
      The other important option that influences the structure of the entire
      file is <guilabel>Single merged abscissa</guilabel>.  By default
      individual curves are written to the file sequentially, separated by
      empty lines.  When this checkbox is enabled the curve export writes
      one multi-column table with data of all curves and a single abscissa in
      the first column.  If the curves are not sampled identically, some rows
      will of course contain values only for some curves.  Exported file with
      two separated curves can look like
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
0.1 3.32e6
0.2 3.80e6
0.4 4.15e6

0.0 11.1
0.3 9.66
0.4 9.70
]]></programlisting>
      </informalexample>
      while with single merged abscissa the same data would be saved
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
0.0 --- 11.1
0.1 3.32e6 ---
0.2 3.80e6 ---
0.3 --- 9.66
0.4 4.15e6 9.70
]]></programlisting>
      </informalexample>
    </para>
    <para>
      It is also possible to export a vector (EPS) or bitmap (PNG) rendering
      of the graph using <guimenuitem>Export PostScript</guimenuitem> or
      <guimenuitem>Export Bitmap</guimenuitem>.  However, these options are
      rather rudimentary.  Gwyddion is not a dedicated plotting software and
      if you want nice graphs use one instead – for instance
      <ulink url='http://www.gnuplot.info/'>gnuplot</ulink>
      or
      <ulink url='http://matplotlib.org/'>matplotlib</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-stats'>
    <title>
      Statistics
      <gwy:icon name='graph_statistics'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>statistics</primary>
      <secondary>graphs</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>mean</primary>
      <secondary>of a graph curve</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>rms</primary>
      <secondary>of a graph curve</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>minimum</primary>
      <secondary>of a graph curve</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>maximum</primary>
      <secondary>of a graph curve</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>median</primary>
      <secondary>of a graph curve</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>integral</primary>
      <secondary>of a graph curve</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      Graph statistics display summary information about entire graph curves
      or selected ranges.  The dialogue shows two main groups of quantities
      that are calculated differently.
    </para>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Simple Parameters</guilabel> are calculated from the set of
      ordinate values, without any regard to abscissae.  This is important to
      keep in mind when the curve is sampled non-uniformly, i.e. the intervals
      between abscissae differ, possibly a lot.  A part of the curve which is
      sampled more densely contains relatively more points and thus also
      influences the result more.  The available parameters include elementary
      characteristics with the same meaning as for
      <link linkend='stat-quantities'>two-dimensional data</link>.
      Several of them also coincide with basic roughness parameters calculated
      by the <link linkend='roughness-iso'>Roughness</link> tool.
    </para>
    <para>
      On the other hand, <guilabel>Integrals</guilabel> are obtained by
      integration, utilising the trapezoid rule (or a similar approximation).
      Therefore, longer intervals contribute more to the results.  Available
      quantities include:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Projected length</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          The length of the selected interval (or the entire abscissa range
          if no interval is selected).
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Developed length</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          Sum of lengths of linear segments connecting curve points.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Variation</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          Integral of absolute value of the derivative – calculated as the sum
          of absolute values of ordinate differences.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Average value</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          Area under the curve divided by the projected length.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Area under curve</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          The total integral (sum of positive and negative area).
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Positive area</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          Integral of portions of the curve where it is positive.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Negative area</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          Integral of portions of the curve where it is negative.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Root mean square</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          Integral of squared values divided by the projected length.
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-sfuncs'>
    <title>Statistical Functions</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>autocorrelation function</primary>
      <secondary>graphs</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>height-height correlation function</primary>
      <secondary>graphs</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>power spectral density function</primary>
      <secondary>graphs</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>height distribution</primary>
      <secondary>graphs</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>angle distribution</primary>
      <secondary>graphs</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      One-dimensional statistical functions are calculated for graphs using
      the same definitions as for images.  They are described in the
      <link linkend='sfunctions'>Statistical Functions tool</link>
      documentation.  The available functions include
      <link linkend='height-angle-distribution'>height and angle
      distributions</link>,
      <link linkend='autocorrelation-1d'>autocorrelation function</link>,
      <link linkend='height-height-correlation-1d'>height-height correlation
      function</link> and
      <link linkend='power-spectral-density-1d'>spectral density</link>.
      They can be calculated for the selected curve or for all curves at once
      if <guilabel>All curves</guilabel> is enabled.
    </para>
    <para>
      A major difference between images and graphs is that graph curves do not
      need to have uniformly spaced abscissa values (uniform sampling).  In
      such case the curve is resampled within the calculation of the
      statistical functions to uniform sampling.  The default sampling step is
      such that the number of points is preserved.  However, it can be modified
      by <guilabel>Oversampling</guilabel> which gives how many more points the
      resampled curve should have compared to the graph curve.  Occasionally it
      may be useful to use oversampling larger than 1 even for regularly
      sampled graph curves.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-fit'>
    <title>
      Function Fitting <gwy:icon name='graph_function'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>fitting</primary>
      <secondary>functions to graph</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      The curve fitting is designed namely for fitting of statistical
      functions used in roughness parameters evaluation.  Therefore most of
      the available functions are currently various statistical functions of
      surfaces with Gaussian or exponential autocorrelation functions.
      Nevertheless it also offers a handful of common general-purpose
      functions.  See the
      <link linkend='fitting-functions'>list of fitting functions</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Within the fitting module you can select the area that should be fitted
      (with mouse or numerically), try some initial parameters, or let the
      module to guess them, and then fit the data using Marquardt-Levenberg
      algorithm.
    </para>
    <para>
      As the result you obtain the fitted curve and the set of its parameters.
      The fit report can be saved into a file using
      <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button.  Pressing
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button adds the fitted curve to the graph, if
      this is not desirable, quit the dialogue with
      <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-graph-fit-screenshot'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='graph_fit.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Curve fitting module dialogue
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='fd-curve-fitting'>
    <title>
      Force-Distance Curve Fitting <gwy:icon name='graph_fd'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>fitting</primary>
      <secondary>force-distance curves</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      The module for fitting of force-distance curves is very similar to
      the general curve fitting module, it is just specialized for
      force-distance curves.  Currently, the module serves for fitting jump-in
      part of force-distance curve (representing attractive forces) using
      different models:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between semisphere and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between pyramid and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between truncated pyramid and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between sphere and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between two spheres
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between cone and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between cylinder and half-space
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        van der Waals force between paraboloid and half-space
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Note that the curve being fitted must be a real force-distance curve, not
      a displacement-distance or sensor-distance curve. Recalculation of
      cantilever deflection into force should be done before calling this
      module.
    </para>
    <para>
      Also note that for small cantilever spring constants the amount of usable
      data in attractive region is limited by effect of jumping into contact.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-critical-dimension'>
    <title>
      Critical Dimension <gwy:icon name='graph_measure'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>critical dimension</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Critical dimension module can be used to fit some
      <quote>typical</quote> objects that are often found while analysing
      profiles extracted from microchips and related surfaces. These objects
      are located in the graph and their properties are evaluated.
    </para>
    <para>
      The user interface of this module is practically the same as of the
      graph fit module.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-graph-cd-screenshot'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='graph_cd.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Critical dimension module dialogue.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-dos-spectrum'>
    <title>
      DOS Spectrum <gwy:icon name='graph_dos'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>DOS spectrum</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
        DOS spectrum module intended to obtain Density-of-States spectra
        from I-V STM spectroscopy. It calculates
        <xi:include href="eq-graph-dos.xml"/> and plots it as graph.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-peaks'>
    <title>
      Find Peaks <gwy:icon name='find_peaks'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>peaks</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      The most prominent peaks in graph curves can be automatically located
      with subsample precision.  You can specify the number of most
      prominent peaks as <guilabel>Number of peaks</guilabel> and the function
      will mark them on the graph.  Peak prominence depends on its height,
      area and distance from other peaks.  Usually the function's idea what
      are the most prominent peaks agrees quite well with human assessment.
      If you disagree with the choice you can ask for more peaks and ignore
      those you do not like.  It is also possible for locate negative peaks,
      i.e. valleys, by enabling option
      <guilabel>Invert (find valleys)</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <para>
      A table of all the peaks is displayed in the left part, sorted according
      to <guilabel>Order peaks by</guilabel>.  Ordering by position means peaks
      are listed as they are displayed on the graph from left to right.
      Prominence order means more significant peaks are listed first.
    </para>
    <para>
      Several basic characteristics are displayed for each peak:
      position (abscissa) <xi:include href="eqi-x.xml"/>,
      height <xi:include href="eqi-h.xml"/>,
      area <xi:include href="eqi-A.xml"/>,
      and width (or variance) <xi:include href="eqi-w.xml"/>.
      The position is calculated by quadratic subpixel refinement of the peak
      maximum.  The remaining quantities depend on how the peak background is
      defined.  Possible choices include <guilabel>Zero</guilabel> meaning
      peaks base is always considered to be zero, and <guilabel>Bilateral
      minimum</guilabel> meaning the peak background is a step function
      passing through the nearest curve minima on the left and right side of
      the peak.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-graph-peaks'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='graph-peaks.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Screenshot of automated graph peak location for a height
          distribution plot.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-measure-period'>
    <title>
      Period/pitch <gwy:icon name='graph_period_measure'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>pitch measurement</primary>
      <secondary>one-dimensional</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      Many methods for measurement of the period/pitch of periodic profiles
      such as gratings have been proposed. The graph period measurment module
      implements several of them (see reference [<link linkend='graph-ref-1'>1</link>]
      for their description). For reasonably well measured gratings all the
      good methods
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Refined Fourier transform</listitem>
      <listitem>Multi-peak ACF</listitem>
      <listitem>Zero crossings</listitem>
      <listitem>Gravity centres</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      should give comparable results, although they differ in sensitivity to
      various artefacts in the data. Refined Fourier transform is the most
      robust for odd shapes of the repeating unit. However, it does not
      provide any error estimate.
    </para>
    <para>
      Two elementary methods are also included, simple Fourier transform and
      simple ACF, which just find the position of the main peak in the power
      spectrum or ACF. They should not be used for evaluation and are present
      mainly for completness.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the profile has been already correctly levelled and the zero line
      selected, the function can evaluate the profile without any preprocessing.
      Otherwise, <guilabel>Subtract background</guilabel> should be checked to
      enabled background removal based on a robust procedure (see again
      [<link linkend='graph-ref-1'>1</link>]). In such case
      <guilabel>Show levelled curve</guilabel> can be used to display the
      preprocessed profile alongside with the unmodified data.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-graph-period'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='graph-period.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Measurement of grating pitch.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-terraces'>
    <title>
      Terraces <gwy:icon name='graph_terrace_measure'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm><primary>terrace measurement</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>amphitheatre measurement</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
      Terrace or amphitheatre-like structures can be measured using
      one-dimensional profiles, similarly as they are measured from image data
      in <link linkend='measure-terraces'>Terraces</link>.  The graph and image
      modules are almost identical.  Therefore, the following only highlights
      the main differences:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Step detection kernel and broadening are one-dimensional.  They are
          still measured in pixels – which correspond to average spacing
          between curve points.  Minimum terrace area is replaced by minimum
          length, measured as the fraction of the total abscissa range.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          There is no masking option.  Instead, terraces can be marked manually
          on the graph using mouse when <guilabel>Select regions
          manually</guilabel> is enabled.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          There is an additional choice in <guilabel>Display</guilabel> menu,
          <guilabel>Step detection</guilabel>.  It shows the results of the
          edge detection filters and marks the selected threshold using a
          dashed red line.  This is one of the most useful graphs for
          parameter tuning.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Pixel area <xi:include href="eqi-A_px.xml"/> is replaced with
          <xi:include href="eqi-N_px.xml"/>, the number of curve points the
          terrace consists of.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <informalfigure id='fig-graph-terraces'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='graph-terraces.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Terrace measurement from a profile, showing marked terraces for an
          amphitheatre structure formed by atomic steps on silicon.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-ref'>
    <title>References</title>
    <para id='graph-ref-1'>
      [1] D. Nečas, A. Yacoot, M. Valtr, P. Klapetek:
      Demystifying data evaluation in the measurement of periodic structures.
      Measurement Science and Technology 34 (2023) 055015,
      <ulink url='http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/1361-6501/acbab3'>10.1088/1361-6501/acbab3</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
