<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: presentations-masks.xml 22939 2020-09-04 14:21:54Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='presentations-masks'>
  <title>Presentations and Masks</title>
  <para>
    Presentations and masks are secondary images with specific functions
    attached to the data.  Presentation is a different image displayed over the
    actual data.   Mask represents an irregular set of selected pixels.
    Their presence is indicated by the flags
    <guilabel>P</guilabel> (presentation) and <guilabel>M</guilabel> (mask) in
    the <link linkend='data-browser-images'>data browser</link>.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-mask-presentation-scheme'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='data-show-mask.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>
          Mask (top), presentation (middle), original data (bottom)
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        Visualization of masks and presentations.  If you look from above they
        can be imagined to be stacked as in the picture.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    Both masks and presentations can be removed from the data by functions
    in the right-click menu of the
    <link linkend='data-windows'>data window</link>, or with
    <link linkend='keyboard-shortcuts'>keyboard shortcuts</link>.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-mask-presentation'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='mask.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>A data field shown with a mask and a presentation</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        Data in default false colour representation (left), with superimposed
        mask visualized with a red colour (centre) and with shading presentation
        (right).
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <sect2 id='presentations-introduction'>
    <indexterm><primary>presentation</primary></indexterm>
    <title>Presentations</title>
    <para>
      Presentations can be used to show the height field in another way than as
      a false colour map of the heights, for instance with shading or with
      highlighted edges.  It is also possible to superimpose an arbitrary data
      field over another one as the presentation.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note the superimposed presentation is really only a presentation, it is
      never used for calculations.  In all data processing functions or tools
      the results are always computed from the original underlying data.  Since
      presentations can be computationally intensive to calculate, they are not
      automatically updated when the underlying data change.  The various
      presentations available are described in section
      <link linkend='presentations'>Presentations</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Since the values of the presentation image have arbitrary absolute
      scale and may not even correspond to any meaningful physical quantity,
      the false colour map ruler on the right side of the
      <link linkend='data-windows'>data window</link> does not
      display any ticks nor the minimum and maximum value when a presentation
      is shown.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='masks-introduction'>
    <indexterm><primary>mask</primary></indexterm>
    <title>Masks</title>
    <para>
      Masks are used for special areal selections, e.g.
      <link linkend='grain-analysis'>grains</link>,
      <link linkend='mask-of-outliers'>defects</link>
      or <link linkend='facet-analysis'>facets with certain orientation</link>.
      Masks can have any shape and within the data window and they are
      visualized by a colour overlaid over the data.  The mask colour and
      opacity can be changed in the right-click context menu of the data
      window.
    </para>
    <para>
      Many functions, especially statistical, levelling and row correction
      functions, can use masks to include or exclude areas from the
      calculation.  This choice is presented as <guilabel>Masking
      Mode</guilabel> with the options to exclude the masked region, include
      only the masked region or ignore the mask and use the entire data.
      Note that this choice is usually displayed only if a mask is present.
    </para>
    <para>
      Since grain marking is the most common use of masks, several functions
      that operate on marked areas are called <quote>grain</quote> functions,
      e.g. Grain Statistics.  Also, a contiguous part of mask is sometimes
      called grain in this guide.  However, since a mask does not bear any
      information how it was created all mask functions can be used with masks
      of any origin.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
