<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: interpolation.xml 22944 2020-09-23 07:49:10Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='smm' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
  <title>Scanning Microwave Microscopy</title>
  <indexterm><primary>smm</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    Scanning Microwave Microscopy is based on measurement of reflection
    coefficients of microwaves applied to a conductive tip. Using 
    vector network analyzer or similar hardware we want to obtain 
    the reflection coefficient <xi:include href="eqi-S11.xml"/> and, out of it,
    to determine tip-sample impedance, capacitance, or any other quantity related
    to it.
  </para>
  <para>
    Here, we describe two modules implementing modified short-open-load
    calibration procedure described in Ref. [<link linkend='smm-ref-1'>1</link>].
    It is based on measurement of a sample with areas of known capacitances,
    e.g. small capacitors acting as reference samples[<link linkend='smm-ref-2'>2</link>],
    and by comparison of theoretical and measurement reflection coefficients
    it establishes complex calibration coefficients that can be used for SMM calibration,
    i.e. to convert measurement on unknown samples to quantitative results.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='smm-calibration'>
    <title>
      SMM calibration
    </title>
    <para>
      Goal of this module is to use data measured on a known sample to determine
      three complex calibration coefficients <xi:include href="eqi-e00.xml"/>, <xi:include href="eqi-e01.xml"/> 
      and <xi:include href="eqi-e11.xml"/> containing infomration about directivity, reflection tracking, 
      source match, merged with information about the local electrical conditions around the 
      tip apex[<link linkend='smm-ref-3'>3</link>]. The coefficients relate the measured reflection
      coefficients <xi:include href="eqi-S11m.xml"/> to intrinstic reflection coefficients 
      <xi:include href="eqi-S11.xml"/> as
    </para>
    <para>
       <xi:include href="eq-smm-direct.xml"/>
    </para>
    <para>
      The intrinstic reflection coefficients are related to complex tip-sample impedance <xi:include href="eqi-ztip.xml"/>
      and reference impedance <xi:include href="eqi-zref.xml"/> as
    </para>
    <para>
       <xi:include href="eq-smm-ztip.xml"/>
    </para>
    <para>
      For a capacitor reference sample, the tip-sample impedance can be calculated from its known capacitance
      (obtained from sample manufacturer or via numerical modeling) and angular frequency of the microwaves as 
    </para> 
    <para>
       <xi:include href="eq-smm-cap.xml"/>
    </para>
    <para>
      The module uses the above three equations to determine the calibration coefficients, either by
      direct solution of the equations for three complex measurements (when only three sets are provided)
      or by fitting all the available data (when more sets are provided). Direct solution is also used 
      for an estimate, using the minimum, maximum and middle of the provided capacitances.
    </para>
    <para>
      Apart of two images representing complex data from VNA (either a pair of real + imaginary or module + phase
      images), user has to provide masks covering the 
      individual surface areas where the capacitance is known and values of this capacitance. These masks
      have to be set up before running the module, either using thresholding or some of the mask edit tools,
      followed by mask extraction, so it resides in the Data Browser as an individual channel. User can 
      check which of the provided sets (mask + capacitance) will be used for calculation or fitting
      of the calibration coefficients.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-smm'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='smm.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>SMM calibration module</phrase>
        </textobject>
        <caption>
          SMM calibration module graphical user interface
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      To test the module, use a
      <ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/projects/gwyddion/files/sample-data/user-guide-examples/smm_user_guide_example.gwy/download">
      sample file</ulink> with pre-processed data, including with few extracted masks, corresponding to capacitances in the
      above figure. This sample file is based on measurements performed by Damien Richert, Laboratoire national de métrologie et d'essais
      and shows MC2 capacitance sample.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='smm-apply'>
    <title>
      Apply SMM Coefficients
    </title>
    <para>
      This module applies known complex calibration coefficients to the measured data, using the same methodology 
      and equations as discussed in the preceding section. As an input, complex data from VNA 
      (either a pair of real + imaginary or module + phase images) are used.
      When data should be converted to capacitance, the 
      microwave frequency and reference impedance has to be supplied.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-smm-apply'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='smm_apply.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Apply SMM calibration module</phrase>
        </textobject>
        <caption>
          SMM calibration application module graphical user interface
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </sect2>
  <sect2 id='smm-ref'>
    <title>References</title>
    <para id='smm-ref-1'>
      [1] Hoffmann, J.; Wollensack, M.; Zeier, M.; Niegemann, J.; Huber, H. A Calibration Algorithm for Nearfield Scanning Microwave
      Microscopes. In Proceedings of the 12th IEEE International Conference on Nanotechnology, IEEE-NANO, Birmingham, UK,
      20–23 August 2012; pp. 1–4.
     <ulink url='https://doi.org/10.1109/NANO.2012.6322116'>doi:10.1109/NANO.2012.6322116</ulink>
    </para>
    <para id='smm-ref-2'>
      [2] Piquemal, F.; Morán-Meza, J.; Delvallée, A.; Richert, D.; Kaja, K., Progress in Traceable Nanoscale Capacitance Measurements 
      Using Scanning Microwave Microscopy. Nanomaterials 2021, 11, 820.
     <ulink url='https://doi.org/10.3390/nano11030820'>doi:10.3390/nano11030820</ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
     [3] A. Buchter, J. Hoffmann, A. Delvallée, E. Brinciotti, D. Hapiuk, Ch. Licitra, K. Louarn, A. Arnoult, 
     G. Almuneau, F. Piquemal, M. Zeier, F. Kienberger, Review of Scientific Instruments 89, 023704 (2018).
     <ulink url='https://doi.org/10.1063/1.5015966'>doi:10.1063/1.5015966</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
