<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: specific-data-import.xml 25931 2023-10-24 12:09:36Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='specific-data-import'>
  <title>Specific Data Import</title>
  <para>
    Import of several other types of data is not automatic and it requires
    human intervention.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='pixmap-file-import'>
    <title>Graphics Formats</title>
    <para>
      Importing data from image formats such as PNG, TIFF, JPEG or BMP is
      similar to import from raw/unknown file formats, only simpler.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is simpler because the file structure is known and the file format is
      automatically detected.  Hence the file type does need to be selected
      explicitly.  However, the data interpretation is still unknown and must
      be specified manually.  The pixmap import dialogue therefore resembles the
      <guilabel>Information</guilabel> tab of raw data import, requiring you to
      set the physical dimensions and value scale.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note the physical dimensions suggested there are <emphasis>not</emphasis> obtained from
      the file, they are simply the last values used.  Some SPM data formats
      are based on an image format (typically, TIFF is used as the base)
      and contain the information about physical scales and units, albeit
      stored in a manufacturer-specific way.  In this case a separate import
      module can be written for this particular format to load the files
      automatically with correctly scaled values.
    </para>
    <para>
      See the reference section <link linkend='pixmap-image-keys'>High-Depth
      Image Formats</link> for the details of support for high-depth images
      and the possibility of using them for data representations.
    </para>
    <para>
      For plain (non-SPM) images there is also an option to <guilabel>Just use
      pixels</guilabel> for the dimensions. This sets the physical dimensions
      equal to the pixel dimensions. They can be still adjusted later, for
      instance using <link linkend='dimensions-and-units'>Dimensions and
      Units</link>.
    </para>
    <sect3 id='pixmap-file-import-volume'>
      <title>Image stack as volume data</title>
      <para>
        A multipage image (image stack) can be also imported as volume data instead
        of a heap of images. It is enabled by <guilabel>Import as volume data</guilabel>.
        This option currently exists only for multipage TIFFs.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <xi:include href="eqi-z.xml"/> coordinate in the imported data is simply the
        image number in the stack (starting from 0). Use volume data
        <link linkend='volume-calibrate'>Dimensions and Units</link> or
        <link linkend='volume-zcalibration'>Z Calibration</link> function
        to set the physical scale and/or units of <xi:include href="eqi-z.xml"/>.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='graph-curve-import'>
    <title>Graph Curves</title>
    <para>
      Simple two-column text files containing curve data can be imported as
      graph curves.  In some cases, these files are recognized automatically.
      They can also be explicitly selected as <guilabel>ASCII graph curve
        files</guilabel> in the file open dialogue, causing the import module to
      try harder to load the file as a graph data.
    </para>
    <para>
      The import dialogue shows a preview of the graph and permits to set the
      units and labels.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='raw-xyz-import'>
    <title>XYZ Data</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>XYZ data</primary>
      <secondary>import</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      Three-column text files containing XYZ data are imported by selecting
      the <guilabel>XYZ data files</guilabel> file type.  Again, they can be
      recognized automatically but requesting this format explicitly makes the
      module to try harder to load the file as
      <link linkend='xyz-data'>XYZ data</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The import dialogue displays the number of points and physical ranges of
      the data and permits setting the lateral and value units.  The displayed
      ranges in physical units are updated according to the units you enter so
      you can immediately see if they they are correct.
    </para>
    <para>
      Occasionally one can encounter image data are stored as XYZ data with
      completely regular lateral coordinates.  Since they are still meant to be
      treated as image data, just in an odd format, the import module attempts
      to detect this situation.  It then offers direct rendering to an image
      instead of importing the file as true XYZ data.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='nmm-xyz-import'>
    <title>Nano Measuring Machine XYZ Data</title>
    <para>
      The Nano Measuring Machine data are sets of often huge XYZ files that
      would be difficult, if even possible to handle normally in Gwyddion.
      Therefore, they are directly rasterised to an image upon import.  Select
      the main description file (<filename>.dsc</filename>) to open the data
      file set and set the import parameters.
    </para>
    <para>
      Usually, the vertical size should be chosen as the number of profiles
      (i.e. number of data files).  However, a larger resolution can be also
      useful.  If you enable the <guilabel>Identical measures</guilabel>
      checkbox then the imported image will have square pixels.  Only one
      resolution can be then entered – the other one is determined
      automatically.
    </para>
    <para>
      On 64bit systems, the import module can currently handle up to
      2<superscript>32</superscript> points per channel while the total number
      of data values is not limited.  Note that reading the data points can
      take considerable time.  Select only channels you are actually interested
      in to speed up the import process.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='nanonis-sxm-import'>
    <title>Nanonis SXM Data</title>
    <para>
      Nanonis uses a right-handed coordinate system and Gwyddion a
      left-handed system.  Hence it is not possible to preserve simultaneously
      how images look visually and the absolute coordinates of images and their
      features – the latter is required for correct import of spectra.
    </para>
    <para>
      The default behaviour was varying between versions.  Since version 2.52
      you can choose it by setting the value of
      <literal>/module/nanonis/preserve_coordinates</literal> in the
      <link linkend='settings'>settings</link>:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <literal>False</literal> means images look the same, but vertical
          coordinates are flipped.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <literal>True</literal> means coordinates are correct, but images
          look flipped vertically.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
