<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: tip.xml 24820 2022-05-12 15:29:21Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='tip-convolution-artefacts'>
  <title>Tip Convolution Artefacts</title>
  <para>
    Tip convolution artefact is one of the most important error sources in
    SPM. As the SPM tip is never ideal (like delta function) we often observe
    a certain degree of image distortion due to this effect. We can even see
    some SPM tips imaged on the surface scan while sharp features are present
    on the surface.
  </para>
  <informalfigure id='fig-tip-alltips-scans'>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref='alltips.png' format='PNG'/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        Images of ZnSe surface measured with four different SPM tips
        (more or less broken ones).
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
    We can fortunately simulate and/or correct the tip effects using
    algorithms of dilation and/or erosion, respectively. These algorithms
    were published by Villarubia
    (see [<link linkend='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref-1'>1</link>]).
  </para>
  <sect2 id='tip-obtaining-geometry'>
    <title>Obtaining the Tip Geometry</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>tip</primary>
      <secondary>modelling</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      For studying the tip influence on the data we need to know tip geometry
      first. In general, the geometry of the SPM tip can be determined in
      several ways:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        Use manufacturer's specifications (tip geometry, apex radius and
        angle).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Use scanning electron microscope of other independent technique to
        determine tip properties.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Use known tip characterizer sample (with steep edges).
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Use blind tip estimation algorithm together with tip characterizers
        or other suitable samples.
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <sect3 id='tip-model'>
      <title>
        Tip Modelling
        <gwy:icon name='tip_model'/>
      </title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Tip and Indentation</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Model Tip</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        Tip modelling implements the first approach. Using tip modelling
        most of the tips with simple geometries can be simulated. This way of
        tip geometry specification can be very efficient namely when we need to
        check only certainty map of perform tip convolution simulation.
      </para>
      <para>
        The function offers several usual model shapes such as pyramids, cones
        or paraboloids.  Each is described by a subset of the following parameters:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Number of sides</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The number of pyramid sides applies to pyramidal tips (which do not
              have a fixed number of sides by definition).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Tip slope</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Angle of the pyramid side, measured from the vertical plane.  Small angles
              mean shallow tips and large angles means sharp tips.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Tip rotation</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Rotation with respect to a base orientation, measured anti-clockwise.  It
              applies to tips which are not rotationally symmetric.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Tip apex radius</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Mean radius of curvature at the tip apex (applies to all tip shapes, except
              the delta-function).  If the tip is not anisotropic, this is simply the radius
              of curvature in all directions.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <guilabel>Tip anisotropy</guilabel>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Ratio expressing how much the tip is squashed along one of the two orthogonal
              directions with respect to the other.  Only the elliptic parabola
              model has an anisotropy parameter.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
        The tip image dimensions are determined automatically using the source data to cover
        the data <xi:include href="eqi-z.xml"/>-range.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id='tip-blind-estimate'>
      <title>
        Blind Estimation of Tip Shape
        <gwy:icon name='tip_estimation'/>
      </title>
      <para>
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
          <guisubmenu>Tip and Indentation</guisubmenu>
          <guimenuitem>Blind Estimation</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
      </para>
      <para>
        To obtain more detailed (and more realistic) tip structure blind tip
        estimation algorithm can be used.
        Blind tip estimation algorithm is an extension of the well-known fact
        that on some surface data we can see images of certain parts of tip
        directly. The algorithm iterates over all the surface data and at each
        point tries to refine each tip point according to steepest slope in the
        direction between concrete tip point and tip apex.
      </para>
      <para>
        We can use two modification of this algorithm within Gwyddion:
        <emphasis>partial</emphasis> tip estimation that uses only limited
        number of highest points on the image and <emphasis>full</emphasis> tip
        estimation that uses full image (and is much slower therefore). Within
        Gwyddion tip estimation module we can use also partial tip estimation
        results as starting point for full estimation. This improves the speed
        of full tip estimation.
      </para>
      <para>
        The typical procedure is
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          Use <guibutton>Reset Tip</guibutton> to start afresh, for instance
          after changing parameters.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Run the partial estimation using <guibutton>Run Partial</guibutton>.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Run the full estimation using <guibutton>Run Full</guibutton>.
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        It is possible – and often useful – to run the full estimate with several
        topographical images in sequence.  This can be achieved by selecting
        successively the images as <guilabel>Related data</guilabel> and running
        the estimation.
      </para>
      <informalfigure id='fig-tip-alltips'>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref='alltips2.png' format='PNG'/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            SPM tips obtained from data of
            <link linkend='fig-tip-alltips-scans'>previous figure</link>
            using blind estimation algorithm.
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>
        The tip shape can change during the scanning.  Therefore, it is sometimes
        useful to inspect how its blind estimation evolves with the scan
        lines.  Of course, estimation from a single scan line is impossible.
        Hence, the image is split to horizontal stripes and the tip is estimated
        for each stripe.
      </para>
      <para>
        The stripe-wise processing is enabled by <guilabel>Split to
        stripes</guilabel>, which also controls the number of stripes.  You can
        choose which tip is displayed using <guilabel>Preview stripe</guilabel>.
        A tip radius graph is displayed below the preview – and can be created
        as output when <guilabel>Plot size graph</guilabel> is enabled.
        The function can also produce the full sequence of estimated tip images,
        which is enabled by <guilabel>Create tip images</guilabel>.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='tip-operations'>
    <title>
      Tip Convolution and Surface Reconstruction
      <gwy:icon name='tip_dilation'/>
      <gwy:icon name='tip_erosion'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>tip</primary>
      <secondary>convolution</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>dilation</primary>
      <secondary>tip</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para id='tip-convolution'>
      When we know tip geometry, we can use tip convolution (dilation)
      algorithm to simulate data acquisition process. For doing this use
      Dilation module
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Tip and Indentation</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Dilation</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>).
      This can be in particular useful when working with data being result of
      some numerical modelling
      (see e.g. [<link linkend='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref-2'>2</link>]).
    </para>
    <para>
      Note this algorithm (as well as the following two) requires compatible
      scan and tip data, i.e. the physical dimensions of a scan pixel and
      of a tip image pixels have to be equal.  This relation is automatically
      guaranteed for tips obtained by blind estimate when used on the same
      data (or data with an identical measure).  If you obtained the tip
      image by other means, you may need to resample it.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-tip-simulated-convolution'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='fractaltips.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Simulated fractal surface before (left) and after (right) tip
          convolution.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para id='tip-surface-reconstruction'>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>tip</primary>
        <secondary>deconvolution</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>erosion</primary>
        <secondary>tip</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      The opposite of the tip convolution is surface reconstruction (erosion)
      that can be used to correct partially the tip influence on image data.
      For doing this, use Surface Reconstruction function
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Tip and Indentation</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Surface Reconstruction</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>).
      Of course, the data corresponding to points in image not touched by tip
      (e. g. pores) cannot be reconstructed as there is no information about
      these points.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-tip-reconstruction'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='reconstruction.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Original and reconstructed image of ZnSe imaged by broken SPM tip.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='tip-certainty-map'>
    <title>
      Certainty Map <gwy:icon name='tip_map'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>tip</primary>
      <secondary>certainty map</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      As it can be seen, the most problematic parts of SPM image are data
      points where tip did not touch the surface in a single point, but in
      multiple points. There is a loss of information in these points.
      Certainty map algorithm can mark points where surface was probably
      touched in a single point.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-tip-certainty-map'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='certainty-map.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Certainty map obtained from standard grating. Note that the modelled
          tip parameters were taken from datasheet here for illustration
          purposes. (left) – sample, (right) – sample with marked
          certainty map.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      Certainty map algorithm can be therefore used to mark data in the SPM
      image that are corrupted by tip convolution in an irreversible way. For
      SPM data analysis on surfaces with large slopes it is important to
      check always presence of these points. Within Gwyddion you can use
      Certainty Map function for creating these maps
      (<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Data Process</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Tip and Indentation</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Certainty Map</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>).
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref'>
    <title>References</title>
    <para id='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref-1'>
      [1] J. S. Villarrubia: Algorithms for Scanned Probe Microscope Image
      Simulation, Surface Reconstruction, and Tip Estimation.
      J. Res. Natl. Inst. Stand. Technol. 102 (1997) 425,
     <ulink url='http://dx.doi.org/10.6028/jres.102.030'>doi:10.6028/jres.102.030</ulink>
    </para>
    <para id='tip-convolution-artefacts-ref-2'>
      [2] P. Klapetek, I. Ohlídal: Theoretical analysis of the atomic force
      microscopy characterization of columnar thin films. Ultramicroscopy 94
      (2003) 19–29,
     <ulink url='http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0304-3991(02)00159-6'>doi:10.1016/S0304-3991(02)00159-6</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
