<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: volume-data-processing.xml 25953 2023-10-26 07:18:36Z klapetek $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='volume-data-processing'>
  <title>Volume Data Processing</title>
  <para>
    Gwyddion currently provides several basic functions for visualisation
    of volume data and extraction of lower-dimensional data (images, curves)
    from them.  A few specialised functions, focused on processing volume
    data as curves (or spectra) in each pixel, are also available.  They are
    all present in the <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu> menu of the toolbox.
  </para>
  <para>
    Volume data are often interpreted in Gwyddion as a set of curves, each
    attached to one pixel in the <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane, or
    alternately stack of images along the <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>
    axis. This means the volume data functions may treat the
    <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/> axis specially.  If you intend to import
    volume data with two spatial and one special dimensions to Gwyddion make
    sure that the special axis corresponds to <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='basic-volume-operations'>
    <title>Basic Operations</title>
    <para>
      Elementary operations with volume data include:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry id='volume-calibrate'>
        <term>
          <guimenuitem>Dimensions and Units</guimenuitem>
          <gwy:icon name='volume_dimensions'/>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            It changes the physical dimensions, units or value scales and also
            lateral offsets. This is useful to correct raw data that have
            been imported with wrong physical scales or as a simple manual
            recalibration of dimensions and values.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='volume-invert'>
        <term>
          <guimenuitem>Invert Value</guimenuitem>
          <gwy:icon name='volume_invert'/>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This function inverts the signs of all values in the volume data.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='volume-extract-preview'>
        <term><guimenuitem>Extract Preview</guimenuitem></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The preview image of the volume data is copied to a new image
            in the file.
            Frequently the preview is an image that could be equivalently
            obtained using <link linkend='volume-slice'>Cut and Slice</link>
            or <link linkend='volume-linestat'>Summarize Profiles</link>.
            And using these functions create images of well-defined quantities.
            However, if you simply want to get the preview image, whatever it
            happens to be, this function will do just that.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='volume-swap-axes'>
        <term>
          <guimenuitem>Swap Axes</guimenuitem>
          <gwy:icon name='volume_swap_axes'/>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Since the <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/> axis is treated somewhat
            differently than the <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane,
            it can be useful to change the roles of the axes.  This function
            rotates and/or mirrors the volume data so that any of the current
            <xi:include href='eqi-x.xml'/>, <xi:include href='eqi-y.xml'/>
            and <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/> axes will become any chosen
            Cartesian axis in the transformed data.
          </para>
          <para>
            The dialogue ensures the transformation is non-degenerate.  When
            you select a transformation that would be degenerate, another axis
            is adjusted to prevent this.  Otherwise, you can perform any
            combination of mirroring and rotations by multiples of 90 degrees
            around Cartesian axes.
          </para>
          <para>
            If the volume data have a <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-axis
            calibration and <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/> becomes some other
            axis the calibration will be lost.  A warning is shown when this
            occurs.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry id='volume-zcalibration'>
        <term>
          <guimenuitem>Z Calibration</guimenuitem>
          <gwy:icon name='volume_calibrate'/>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When the <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-axis is non-spatial the
            sampling along it may be sometimes irregular, unlike the imaging
            axes <xi:include href='eqi-x.xml'/>
            and <xi:include href='eqi-y.xml'/> that are always regular.  In
            Gwyddion this is represented by associating certain
            one-dimensional data with the
            <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-axis, called the Z calibration.
          </para>
          <para>
            This function can display the Z calibration, remove it, extract it
            as a graph curve, take calibration from another volume data or
            attach a new calibration from a text file.
            For attaching a calibration, each line of the file must contain
            one value specifying the true <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-axis
            value for the corresponding plane and, of course, the number of
            lines must correspond to the number of image planes in the volume
            data.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='volume-slice'>
    <title>
      Image and Profile Extraction <gwy:icon name='volume_slice'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      Profiles along any axis and image slices in planes orthogonal to any axis
      can be extracted with
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Cut and Slice</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The image slice in the selected plane, called <guilabel>Base
      plane</guilabel>, is always shown in the left part and the profile along
      the remaining orthogonal axis is shown in the right part of the dialogue.
      You can change the where the line profile is taken by moving the selected
      point in the image.  Conversely, the image plane location can be moved by
      selecting a point in the profile graph.  Both can be also entered
      numerically as <guilabel>X</guilabel>, <guilabel>Y</guilabel>
      and <guilabel>Z</guilabel> (in pixel coordinates).
    </para>
    <para>
      You can choose between image and profile extraction freely by changing
      <guilabel>Output type</guilabel>.  Changing the output type only
      influences whether the module creates the image on the left or the
      profile graph on the right when you press <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is also possible to take multiple profiles or image slices at the
      same time.  If <guilabel>Extract multiple items</guilabel> is enabled
      a list of selected points will appear on the right.  In this case the
      output type influences the selection.  In the
      <guilabel>Image slice</guilabel> mode you can select only one point in
      the image (determining the profile shown in the graph) but multiple
      points in the graph, each determining one output image plane.
      Conversely, in the <guilabel>Line graph</guilabel> mode you can select
      only one point in the graph (determining the image plane shown) but
      multiple points in the image, determining where the line profiles will
      be taken.
    </para>
    <para>
      Switching betwen the output types when mutli-item extraction is enabled
      reduces the selected coordinate set to a single point.  You can also use
      the <guibutton>Reset</guibutton> button to reduce the selection to the
      default single point if you want to start afresh.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-volume-slice'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='volume-slice.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Screenshot of the Cut and Slice volume data processing module,
          showing the simultaneous extraction of three line profiles along
          the <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-axis.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='volume-export-text'>
    <title>Text Export</title>
    <para>
      Volume data can be exported to text files in several formats using
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Export Text</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      The possible output formats are
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          VTK structured grid
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Format indented for direct loading into
            <ulink url='https://www.vtk.org/'>VTK</ulink>-based software
            such as <ulink url='https://www.paraview.org/'>ParaView</ulink>.
            The values are dumped as a block of <code>STRUCTURED_POINTS</code>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          One Z-profile per line
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Each line of the output file consists of one
            <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-profile.  There are as many lines
            as there are points in each <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/>
            plane (image) of the volume data.  The profiles are ordered by row,
            then by column (the usual order for image pixels).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          One XY-layer per line
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Each line of the output file consists of one
            <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> image plane, stored by row, then
            by column (the usual order for image pixels).  There are as many
            lines as there are <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-levels in the
            volume data.  The layers are stored in order of increasing
            <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          Blank line separated matrices
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Each line of the output file consists of one image row in one
            <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane.  After one entire plane is
            stored a blank line separates the next plane. The layers again
            stored in order of increasing <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='volume-linestat'>
    <title>
      Line Profile Characterisation <gwy:icon name='volume_line_stats'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      Basic overall characterisation of profiles along the
      <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-axis can be performed using
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Summarize Profiles</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      This function creates an image formed by statistical characteristics of
      profiles taken along the <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-axis.  The
      set of available statistical quantities is the same as in the
      <link linkend='line-stats'>Row/column statistics tool</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The dual image/graph selection generally works very similarly to
      <link linkend='volume-slice'>Image and profile extractions</link>.
      The main difference is that an interval can be selected in the graph,
      defining the part of the image stack from which the statistical
      characteristics will be calculated.  The interval can be also entered
      numerically using the <guilabel>Range</guilabel> entries.
    </para>
    <para>
      The image on the left shows the calculated characteristics and
      corresponds to the output of the module.  Selecting a different point in
      the image changes the profile displayed in the graph, which can be useful
      for choosing a suitable range.  The value for the selected profile is
      displayed below the statistical quantity selector.  However, choosing
      a profile does not influence the output in any way.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='volume-planestat'>
    <title>
      Plane Characterisation <gwy:icon name='volume_plane_stats'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      Basic overall characterisation of <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> planes
      can be performed using
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Summarize Planes</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
      This function creates a graph formed by statistical characteristics of
      individual <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/>-planes in the volume data
      or their parts.  The set of available quantities is a subset of those
      calculated by <link linkend='stat-quantities'>Statistical quantities
      tool</link>.  A few quantities can take some time to calculate for all
      layers.
    </para>
    <para>
      The dual image/graph selection generally works very similarly to
      <link linkend='volume-slice'>Image and profile extractions</link>.
      The main difference is that a rectangular region can be selected in the
      image plane, defining a rectangle from which the statistical
      characteristics will be calculated.  The rectangle can be also entered
      numerically using the <guilabel>Origin</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>Size</guilabel> controls.
    </para>
    <para>
      The graph on the right shows the calculated characteristics and
      corresponds to the output of the module.  Selecting a different position
      in the graph changes the <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane displayed
      in the image, which can be useful for choosing a suitable region.  The
      value for the selected plane is displayed below the statistical
      quantity selector.  However, choosing a plane does not influence the
      output in any way.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='volume-arithmetic'>
    <title>
      Arithmetic
      <gwy:icon name='volume_arithmetic'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      Arithmetic with volume data works exactly the same as
      <link linkend='data-arithmetic'>image data arithmetic</link>,
      including the same
      <link linkend='expression-syntax'>expression syntax</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The preview shows the average over all levels and the set of automatic
      variables is slightly different:
    </para>
    <para>
      <informaltable id='table-volume-arithmetic-variables'>
        <tgroup cols='2'>
          <?dblatex lX?>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Variable</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>d1</varname>, …, <varname>d8</varname></entry>
              <entry>
                Data value at the voxel.  The value is in base physical units,
                e.g. for current of 15 nA, the value of <varname>d1</varname>
                is 1.5e-8.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>x</varname></entry>
              <entry>
                Horizontal coordinate of the voxel (in real units).  It is the
                same in all volume data due to the compatibility requirement.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>y</varname></entry>
              <entry>
                Vertical coordinate of the voxel (in real units).  It is
                the same in all volume data due to the compatibility
                requirement.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>z</varname></entry>
              <entry>
                Depth (level) coordinate of the voxel (in real units).  It is
                the same in all volume data due to the compatibility
                requirement.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><varname>zcal</varname></entry>
              <entry>
                Calibrated <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-coordinate of the
                voxel (in real units) if the volume data have
                <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-axis calibration
                (see <link linkend='volume-zcalibration'>Z calibrations</link>).
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='volume-clustering'>
    <title>
      K-means and K-medians clustering
      <gwy:icon name='volume_kmeans'/>
      <gwy:icon name='volume_kmedians'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      Techniques of imaging spectroscopy like F-D in QNM (Quantitative Nanomechanical Mapping) applications,
      I-V in semiconductor engineering, Raman in material characterization
      require to measure spectrum per each point of data grid on sample surface.
      Working with obtained array is not so simple, as we need to work with
      thousands of spectra and analyze each of them. If the sample of interest
      has limited number of regions with very similar spectra inside each region,
      some technique grouping similar spectra together can be of great help.
      One possible way of doing so is using clustering analysis. In
      <application>Gwyddion</application> currently two methods is implemented:
      K-means and K-medians.
    </para>
    <para>
      Both algorithms are intended to find <xi:include href='eqi-K.xml'/> clusters with similar spectra
      inside the cluster and maximally different between clusters. So
      <guilabel>Number of clusters</guilabel> is how many clusters <xi:include href='eqi-K.xml'/> you
      want to obtain in the result. <guilabel>Convergence precision digits</guilabel>
      and <guilabel>Max. iterations</guilabel> regulate convergence
      criteria of algorithms that stop either if required precision of cluster centers
      position is achieved or allowed number of convergence cycles is exceeded.
      Higher precision require more steps to achieve, second limit is mostly
      intended to get rid of endless loops if the precision is to high for
      this set of data.
    </para>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Normalize</guilabel> is somewhat experimental technique that
      qives nice results for imaging spectroscopy. If you are not interested
      in spectral intensities and want to cluster data by similarity of
      middle-frequencies of spectral features (it is typical, for example, for Raman
      microscopy), than enable this checkbox. It removes low frequency background by
      substraction of minimum withing the moving window, and then normalizes spectrum
      to make average intensity be equal 1.0. Both modules outputs two datafields:
      one shows to which cluster belongs the current spectrum, another shows error —
      difference between the current spectrum and center of corresponding cluster.
      If normalization is enabled than third datafield shows values the spectral
      intensities was divided by during normalization (after low-freq. filtering).
      Also graph with spectra corresponding to the centers of clusters is extracted.
    </para>
    <para>
      Algorithms beside this two modules are based on usual unsupervized learning clustering:
      K-means and K-medians, correspondingly. We consider each spectrum (graph extracted along
      <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/>-axis) to be the point in multidimensial space
      with the number of dimensions equal number of data point in the graph. We define
      distance between points as square root from sum of squared differencies along
      each direction (<xi:include href='eqi-L-to-2.xml'/>-norm). Than we initialize both algorithms by choosing random <xi:include href='eqi-K.xml'/> points
      from the volume data as cluster centers. Than the usual two step algorithm is applied:
      we assign each point to the cluster whose center is nearest to the point and then move
      centers of the clusters. The difference between two modules is how to
      calculate the cluster center: it is mean value of cluster points for K-means and median
      along each direction for K-medians. The results from the last iteration are
      returned back to the program.
    </para>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Remove outliers</guilabel> for K-means modifies algorithm
      for calculation of cluster centers to include only datapoints within
      <guilabel>Outliers threshold</guilabel> multiplied by data variation
      <xi:include href='eqi-sigma.xml'/> for each cluster.
      It removes single distinct bogus data points (like spikes,
      cosmic rays in Raman spectroscopy and so on) from calculation,
      making cluster centers somewhere more clean and distinct
      and also can shift border between intermixing clusters to more
      correct place between two centers of maximal point densities not
      disturbed by far outliers.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='volume-mfm'>
    <title>Magnetic force microscopy</title>
    <para>
      A few volume data functions are dedicated to MFM data processing.  They
      are generally analogous to their image counterparts.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-mfm-data-conversion'>
      Conversion of MFM data to force gradient is exactly the same for volume
      and image data.  Therefore, the summary of
      <link linkend='mfm-data-conversion'>image MFM data conversion</link>
      applies to volume data unchanged.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-transfer-function-guess'>
      The transfer function estimation
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Transfer Function Guess</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      is also quite similar to
      <link linkend='transfer-function-guess'>image transfer function
      estimation</link>.  The TF is estimated for each level in the volume data
      and its various properties plotted as graphs.  Which graphs are
      plotted can be selected in the <guilabel>Output Options</guilabel> tab.
      The regularisation parameter <xi:include href='eqi-sigma.xml'/> can be
      the same for all levels, or it can be estimated for each level by
      enabling <guilabel>Estimate sigma for each level</guilabel>.  The
      computation then takes notably longer.  For the <guilabel>Least
      squares</guilabel> method, even the transfer function size can be
      estimated for each level when <guilabel>Estimate size for each
      level</guilabel> is enabled.  The size given in the dialogue then
      determines the size of the output – and thus maximum possible size.
      Smaller transfer functions are extended with zeros to this size.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-stray-field'>
      The stray field consistency check
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Stray Field Consistency</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      recalculates the field to a different height similarly to
      <link linkend='mfm-field-shift'>MFM field shift</link>.  However, since
      the volume data contains images corresponding to many different levels,
      it is possible to calculate the field for each and compare it to the
      calculated field.  And this is what the module does.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
