<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: volume-data-processing.xml 25933 2023-10-24 12:13:10Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='image-stacks-processing'>
  <title>Volume Data Processing: Image stacks</title>
  <para>
    Volume data can be also used to represent stacks of images, i.e. coming
    from high-speed Scanning Probe Microscopy, representing multiple measurements
    of the sample, either on the same place or when moving laterally.
    In this case the data should be loaded as stack of images along
    the <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/> axis.
    Such data can be processed by specialized functions available
    in the <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu> menu of the toolbox, mostly described
    in this part of the User Guide. On top of it, the general functions for
    handling Volume data can be used as well.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='image-stack-correction'>
    <title>XY Plane Correction</title>
    <para>
      A few simple corrections or adjustments can be applied automatically
      to each <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane in the volume data.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-plane-level'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>XY Plane Level</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      applies plane levelling to each plane.  In other words, it subtracts the
      mean plane from all images formed by <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/>
      planes. Each plane is treated separately.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-mean-plane-level'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>XY Mean Plane Level</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      applies plane levelling using the same plane, the mean one, to each plane
      in the image stack. It calculates a single mean plane from all the images
      formed by <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> planes, and subtracts the
      mean plane from all the images.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-facet-level'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>XY Facet Level</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      applies facet leveling to all the images
      formed by <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> planes,
      see description of the <link linkend='facet-level'>Facet Level</link> algorithm
      for more details. Each plane is treated separately.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-flatten-base'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>XY Flatten Base</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      applies flatten base algorithm to all the images
      formed by <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> planes,
      see description of the <link linkend='facet-level'>Flatten Base</link> algorithm
      fro more details. Each plane is treated separately.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-step-line'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Step Line Correction</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      applies step line correction algorithm to all the images
      formed by <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> planes,
      see description of the
      <link linkend='line-correction-step'>Step Line Correction module for images</link>.
      Each plane is treated separately.
    </para>
     <para id='volume-outliers'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>XY Plane Outliers</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      replaces the outliers in each <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane by
      the mean value of this plane.  Outliers are defined here as values lying
      farther than three standard deviations from the mean.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-1dfft-filtering'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>1D FFT Filtering</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      performs 1D FFT filtering in each <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane.
      The power spectrum shown in the graph can be calculated for every plane
      individually, or it can be averaged from all the planes. By changing the preview
      level, one can go through all the planes and cross-check the filtering
      impact. Mouse selection in the graph and the suppression methods have same logic
      as in the <link linkend='fft-filter-1d'>1D FFT Filtering module for images</link>.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-scars'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Scars</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      performs detection and removal of scars (fast scanning axis feedback loop errors)
      in each <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane. Each plane is treated separately
      and preview z level can be used to go through them.
      Scars detection method is same as in the
      <link linkend='mark-scars'>Mark Scars module for images</link>.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-drift'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Correct Data</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Estimate Drift</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      performs detection and removal of drift
      in each <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane. Drift is detected by cross-correlation
      which can be applied either to adjacent planes, one by one, which is optimal for
      larger drifts observed during the image stack acquisition, or an average plane
      can be used as a reference, which is optimal for small drifts or noisy data.
      Preview z level can be used to go through the planes, including visualisation
      of the cropped data after application of drift correction. On top of XYZ drift
      estimation, the images can be also rotated in given range, searching for the rotation
      angle which gives the best correlation score.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-volume-drift'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='volume-drift.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Estimate drift dialogue showing detected drift and cropped data.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-superresolution'>
    <title>Super-resolution methods</title>
    <para>
      When multiple images of the same surface area are measured and the image stack is
      stored as Volume data, they can be used for a super-resolution image calculation,
      e.g. using some hypothesis about sample statistical parameters.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-localisation-merge'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>SPM Modes</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>Localization Merge</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      performs the localisation algorithm [<link linkend='image-stacks-ref-1'>1</link>].
      At every <xi:include href='eqi-xy.xml'/> plane the local peaks are detected,
      a probability for peak location is expressed and summed across the planes.
      The method works best on biomolecules or similar objects consisting of
      resolvable peaks, lying on a flat surface, and can remove the tip convolution
      impact and provide a high resolution image from series of low resolution ones.
      An important assumption is that the tip touches slightly different parts of the
      object at each scan, making the method well suited to soft samples in liquid
      environment. Note that the individual frames have to be aligned to display the
      same area of the surface, for this, e.g. the <link linkend='volume-drift'>Estimate Drift</link>
      module can be used.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-volume-lafm'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='volume-lafm.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          A single high-speed AFM frame and a localisation microscopy algorithm result,
          data courtesy of George R. Heath and Simon Scheuring.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-stitch'>
    <title>Stitching</title>
    <para>
      When the image stack represents different areas on the surface, a merged data
      representing larger area of the surface can be created. For this an information
      coming from sample coarse motion stage or from detected image overlaps can be used.
    </para>
    <para id='volume-stitch'>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Volume Data</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>SPM Modes</guisubmenu>
        <guimenuitem>XY Stitch</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      performs stitching of a set of images represented as volume data, using
      the overlaps to minimize mutual offsets and using graphs of X and Y translations
      between the images. The X and Y translations are in base units (i.e. usually meters)
      and its X axis is treated as the frame number.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-xy-stitch'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='volume-xy-stitch.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Volume data stitching example, showing one of 32 images taken on MetExSPM project
          test sample (manufactured by PTB), coarse movement stage data in X axis 
          and the stitched data preview in the module GUI. 
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='image-stacks-ref'>
    <title>References</title>
    <para id='image-stacks-ref-1'>
      [1] G.R Heath, E. Kots, J.L. Robertson, et al.:
      Localization atomic force microscopy.
      Nature 594 (2021) 385–390,
     <ulink url='http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-03551-x'>10.1038/s41586-021-03551-x</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
