<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- @(#) $Id: xyz-data-processing.xml 23026 2020-12-28 09:06:18Z yeti-dn $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN'
               'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd'>
<sect1 id='xyz-data-processing'>
  <title>XYZ Data Processing</title>
  <indexterm><primary>XYZ data</primary></indexterm>
  <para>
    The XYZ data processing possibilities are currently rather limited.
    Most analysis has to be done after their conversion to an image – the basic type of
    data for which <application>Gwyddion</application> offers plenty of
    functions.
  </para>
  <para id='xyzops'>
    Basic XYZ data operations currently include merging of two point sets,
    available as
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>XYZ Data</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Merge</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>.
    Merging can avoid creation of points at exactly the same lateral
    coordinates.  Instead, their values are averaged – this is enabled by
    <guilabel>Average coincident points</guilabel>.
  </para>
  <sect2 id='xyz-rasterize'>
    <title>
      Rasterization <gwy:icon name='rasterize'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>XYZ Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Rasterize</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      <application>Gwyddion</application> excels at working with data sampled
      in a regular grid, i.e. image data.  To apply its data processing
      functions to irregular XYZ data, such data must be interpolated to a
      regular grid.  In other words, rasterized.
    </para>
    <para>
      Several interpolation methods are available, controlled bu the
      <guilabel>Interpolation type</guilabel> option:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Round</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This interpolation is analogous to the Round (nearest neighbour)
            interpolation for regular grids.  The interpolated value in a point
            in the plane equals to the value of the nearest point in the XYZ
            point set.  This means the Voronoi tessellation is performed and
            each Voronoi cell is <quote>filled</quote> with the value of the
            nearest point.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Linear</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This interpolation is analogous to the Linear interpolation for
            regular grids.  The interpolated value in a point is calculated
            from the three vertices of the Delaunay triangulation triangle
            containing the point.  As the tree vertices uniquely determine
            a plane in the space, the value in the point is defined by this
            plane.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Field</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The value in a point is the weighted average of all the XYZ point
            set where the weight is proportional to the inverse fourth power of
            the mutual distance.  Since all XYZ data points are considered for
            the calculation of each interpolated point this method can be very
            slow.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Average</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Ad hoc method obtaining pixel values using a combination of simple
            averaging and propagation.  In dense locations where many XYZ
            points fall into a single pixel the value assigned to such pixel
            is a sort of weighted mean value of the points.  In sparse
            locations where relatively large regions contain no XYZ data points
            the pixel value is propagated from close pixels that contain some
            XYZ data points.  The main feature of this interpolation type is
            that it is always fast while often producing quite an acceptable
            result.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The first two interpolation types are based on Voronoi tessellation and
      Delaunay triangulation that is not well-defined for point sets where more
      than two points lie on a line or more than three lie on a circle.  If
      this happens the triangulation can fail and an error message is
      displayed.
    </para>
    <para>
      The values outside the convex hull of the XYZ point set in the plane are
      influenced by <guilabel>Exterior type</guilabel>:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Border</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The point set is not amended in any manner and the values on the
            convex hull simply extend to the infinity.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mirror</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The point set is amended by points <quote>reflected</quote> about
            the bounding box sides.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Periodic</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The point set is amended by periodically repeated points from
            around the opposite side of bounding box.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The horizontal and vertical pixel dimensions of the resulting image
      are specified as <guilabel>Horizontal size</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>Vertical size</guilabel> in the <guilabel>Resolution</guilabel>
      section.
    </para>
    <para>
      Often resulting image should have square pixels. This can be achieved by
      pressing button <guibutton>Make Pixels Square</guibutton>. The function
      does not try to enforce square pixels during the resolution and range
      editing to avoid changing values that you in fact want to keep.  So you
      always need to make the pixels square explicitly.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is possible to rasterize only a portion of the XYZ data and also
      render a part of their exterior.  The region to render to image is
      controlled by the ranges specified in the <guilabel>Physical
      Dimensions</guilabel> section of the dialogue.  Button
      <guibutton>Reset Ranges</guibutton> sets the region to a rectangle
      containing the XYZ data completely.  It is also possible to select the
      region to render on the preview, of course provided that it lies
      inside the currently displayed region.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-triangulation'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='triangulation.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='triangulation.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Delaunay triangulation displayed on top of (a) Linear, (b) Round,
          (c) Field and (d) Average interpolations of an irregular set of
          points.  Since the points are sparse, Average interpolation is quite
          similar to Round, only a bit blurred.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      If the XYZ data represent an image, i.e. the points form a regular grid
      oriented along the Cartesian axes with each point in a rectangular
      region present exactly once, the rasterization function can directly
      produce the corresponding image.  This is done using button
      <guibutton>Create Image Directly</guibutton> that appears at the top
      of the dialogue in this case.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='xyz-level'>
    <title>
      Levelling
      <gwy:icon name='fix_zero'/>
      <gwy:icon name='level'/>
    </title>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>XYZ Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fix Zero</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>XYZ Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Plane Level</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      The basic <guimenuitem>Fix Zero</guimenuitem> function is exactly the
      same as <link linkend='fix-zero'>Fix Zero</link> for image data.  It
      shifts all values to make the minimum equal to zero.
    </para>
    <para>
      <guimenuitem>Plane Level</guimenuitem> removes the mean plane.  It
      offers two methods.  <guilabel>Subtraction</guilabel> is completely
      analogous to <link linkend='plane-level'>Plane Level</link> for image
      data and consists in simple subtraction of the mean plane which is
      found using ordinary least-squares method.
    </para>
    <para>
      <guilabel>Rotation</guilabel> removes the mean plane by true rotation of
      the point cloud, an operation exactly possibly only with XYZ data (the
      corresponding <link linkend='level-rotate'>Level Rotate</link> for images
      is approximate).  Furthermore, the function ensures that the mean plane
      is horizontal after rotation, which corresponds to removal of mean
      plane in the total least-squares sense.  Of course, since rotation
      mixes lateral coordinates and data values, it is only possible when
      <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/> is the same physical quantity as
      <xi:include href='eqi-x.xml'/> and <xi:include href='eqi-y.xml'/>
      (presumably length).
    </para>
    <para>
      Rotation changes the
      <xi:include href='eqi-x.xml'/> and <xi:include href='eqi-y.xml'/>
      point coordinates, potentially making the XYZ data incompatible with
      other data in the file.  By enabling <guilabel>Update X and Y of all
      compatible data</guilabel> you can update the lateral coordinates of all
      other XYZ data sets in the file to match the lateral coordinates in the
      current one after rotation.  The <xi:include href='eqi-z.xml'/> values of
      the other data are, of course, kept intact.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id='fit-shape'>
    <title>
      Fit Shape <gwy:icon name='fit_shape'/>
    </title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>fitting</primary>
      <secondary>3D shapes to XYZ data</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>XYZ Data</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Fit Shape</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
    </para>
    <para>
      This function is also available for images.  See
      <link linkend='fit-shape-image'>Fit Shape for images</link> for
      differences between the image and XYZ variants.
    </para>
    <para>
      Least-squares fitting of geometrical shapes and other predefined
      functions to the entire data can serve diverse purposes: removal of
      overall form such as spherical surface, measurement of geometrical
      parameters or creation of idealised data matching imperfect real
      topography.  It is also possible to use the module for generation of
      artificial data if nothing is fitted and all the geometrical parameters
      are entered explicitly, altough this still requires providing input data
      that define the XY points.
    </para>
    <para>
      The basic usage requires choosing the type of shape to fit, selected as
      <guilabel>Function type</guilabel> (see the
      <link linkend='fitting-3d-shapes'>description of fitting shapes</link>),
      and pressing the following three buttons in given order:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton>Estimate</guibutton></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Automatic initial estimate of the parameters.  Usually the initial
            estimate is sufficient to proceed with fitting.  When it is too off
            it may be necessary to adjust some of the parameters manually to
            help the least-squares fitting find the correct minimum.  For some
            functions the estimation uses a randomly chosen subset of the input
            data to avoid taking too much time.  Hence it is non-deterministic
            and pressing the button again can result in a somewhat different
            initial parameter estimate.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton>Quick Fit</guibutton></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Least-squares fit using a randomly chosen subset of the input data.
            For large input data it is much faster than the full fit but in
            most cases it will converge to parameters quite close to final.  It
            allows checking quickly whether the least-squares method is going
            to converge to the expected minimum – and simultaneously getting
            the parameters values closer to this minimum for the subsequent
            full fit.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton>Fit</guibutton></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
             Full least-squares fit using the entire data.  This can take some
             time, especially for large input data and functions that are slow
             to evaluate.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The residual mean square difference per input point is displayed below
      the tabs as <guilabel>Mean square difference</guilabel>.  It is
      recalculated whenever the preview is recalculated, so not only after
      fitting but also after estimation and manual adjustments.
    </para>
    <para>
      The basic controls in the first tab also allow selecting the output
      from the fitting, which can be either the fitted shape, the difference
      between input data and fitted shape, or both.
    </para>
    <para>
      The preview image can show either the input data, the fitted shape or
      the difference between the two – which is usually the most useful option.
      The difference can be displayed with an adapted color map in which
      red color means the input data are above the fitted shape and blue color
      means the input data are below the fit.  This is enabled with
      <guilabel>Show differences with adapted color map</guilabel>.
    </para>
    <informalfigure id='fig-fit-shape'>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='fit-shape.pdf' format='PDF'/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref='fit-shape.png' format='PNG'/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          Shape fitting example:
          (a) original topographial data of a ring structure on the surface
              of a thin film,
          (b) fitting dialog with parameters on the right side and difference
              between data and fit displayed in the left part,
          (c) resulting fitted shape.
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Parameters</guilabel> tab displays the values of all
      fitting parameters and their errors and allows their precise control.
      Each parameter can be free or fixed.  Fixed parameters are not touched
      by any estimation or fitting function; they are kept at the value you
      entered.  When you change parameter value manually the preview is not
      recalculated automatically – press <guibutton>Recalculate
      Image</guibutton> to update it.  Button <guibutton>Revert to Previous
      Values</guibutton> allows returning to the previous parameter set.  For
      estimation, fitting or manual manipulation this means the set of
      parameter values before the operation modified them.  For reverting it
      means the parameter set before reverting – so pressing the button
      repeatedly alternates between the last two parameter sets.
    </para>
    <para>
      Tab <guilabel>Correlation Matrix</guilabel> displays, after a successful
      fit, the correlation matrix.  Correlation coefficients that are very
      close to unity (in absolute value) are highlighted.
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, tab <guilabel>Derived Quantities</guilabel> displays various
      useful values calculated from fitting parameters.  Some functions have no
      derived quantities, some have several.  Most derived quantities represent
      parameters that you may be interested in more than in the actual fitting
      parameters but that are unsuitable as fitting parameters due to problems
      with numerical stability.  The derived quantities are displayed with
      error estimates, calculated using law of error propagation (including
      parameter correlations).
    </para>
    <para>
      A typical example is the curvature of spherical surface versus its radius
      of curvature.  While the radius is more common it goes from infinity to
      negative infinity when the surface changes between convex and concave
      (i.e. is very close to flat), making it unsuitable as a fitting
      parameter.  In contrast, curvature is zero for a flat surface.
      Therefore, curvature is used as the fitting parameter and the radius of
      curvature is displayed as a derived quantity.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 sw=2 et : -->
